Guide to the Edith Banfield Jackson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edith Banfield Jackson papers
1947-1959
MS 1296
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.25
The papers include photographs, scrapbooks, correspondence, and memorabilia documenting Edith B. Jackson's Yale Rooming-In Research Project at the Grace-New Haven Community Hospital in New Haven, Connecticut. The impact of the rooming-in concept on the medical profession is also documented.
Jackson, Edith Banfield, 1895-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Separated Materials
Models of the rooming-in unit that were originally part of the collection were transferred to the Yale-New Haven Hospital, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by record type.
Biographical / Historical
Edith Banfield Jackson was born in 1895. A graduate of Vassar College (B.A. 1916) and John Hopkins University (M.D. 1921), Jackson held various teaching positions at the Yale University School of Medicine from 1924 to 1929. After a brief hiatus in which she underwent training and analysis with Sigmund Freud, she returned to Yale in 1936 as professor in pediatrics and psychiatry and remained until her retirement in 1959. A child psychiatrist and pioneer in family-centered maternity and infant care and parent-infant bonding, she is best known for her work on the Yale Rooming-In Research Project. She developed the rooming-in plan to allow parents to have an increased role in the care of their newborn children within hospitals. From 1946 to 1952 Jackson directed the experimental rooming-in unit at the Grace-New Haven Community Hospital. The project served as the model for a new obstetrical unit at Yale-New Haven Hospital and stimulated change in the institutionalized care of mothers and infants.
Scope and Contents
The papers include photographs, scrapbooks, correspondence, and memorabilia documenting Edith B. Jackson's Yale Rooming-In Research Project at the Grace-New Haven Community Hospital in New Haven, Connecticut. The impact of the rooming-in concept on the medical profession is also documented.
Medicine; Newborn infants -- Care; Scrapbooks; Jackson, Edith Banfield, 1895-1977; Grace-New Haven Community Hospital
- Inventory
  - Guestbook, 1947-1952 (Box 1)
  - Plaque, [1950] (Box 1A)
  - Scrapbooks with clippings, programs, and letters
    - 1946-1948 (Box 1B)
    - 1949-1951 (Box 1C)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1D)
  - Scrapbook with clippings, programs, and letters, 1954-1959 (Box 2)
  - Floorplan of Rooming-in Unit, Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs depicting labor, delivery, rooming-in in Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Glass slides, circa 1950s (Box 4)